A Guide to the Office of Commonwealth Preparedness, 1999-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Office of Commonwealth Preparedness, 1999-2006
The Library of Virginia
42403
16.45 cubic feet
Virginia Office of Commonwealth Preparedness
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Office of Commonwealth Preparedness on 12 January 2006.
Historical Information
The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness originated from Governor James Gilmore's Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel created after the September 11th terrorist attacks to better prevent and respond to such attacks in Virginia. Shortly thereafter, Governor-elect Mark R. Warner named John H. Hager to the newly created position of assistant to the governor for commonwealth preparedness, now a cabinet-level position, on 28 December 2001. Hager served as lieutenant governor under Governor James Gilmore and was a member of the Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel. On 31 January 2002, Governor Warner issued Executive Order 7, also known as the Secure Virginia Initiative, which rescinded Gilmore's Virginia Preparedness and Security Panel. Executive Order 7 also created the Secure Virginia Panel to review, evaluate, and make recommendations relating to emergency preparedness for the Commonwealth. The Secure Virginia Panel, which became the Secure Commonwealth Panel under Executive Order 69, was to consist of twenty members, later increased to twenty-eight members, under the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness as chairman. The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness and the Secure Commonwealth Panel were later codified under 2.2-304 through 2.2-306 of the Code of Virginia. The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness was created with the purpose of developing a coordinated security and preparedness strategy and implementation plan. The Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness, who is appointed by the governor for a term of four years, is responsible for the general management of the Office. In addition, the Assistant also serves as the point of contact with the federal Department of Homeland Security and as vice-chairman of the Virginia Military Advisory Council. As noted above, John H. Hager was appointed as the first Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. Hager served in this capacity until 1 May 2004 when he was nominated by President George Bush as Assistant Secretary for Special Education. George Williamson Foresman, who served as Deputy Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness, succeeded Hager.
Scope and Content
The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness records consist of forty-seven archival boxes and are divided into seven series. Series have been designated for Appointment Calendars, Cabinet Meeting Files, Constituent Correspondence, Correspondence, Homeland Security Threat Conditions, Secure Commonwealth Panel, and Supporting Documentation. These records document the work of the Office of Commonwealth Preparedness created by Governor Mark R. Warner under the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. The bulk of the records can be found in the Supporting Documentation series related to base closings, homeland security grants, the National Capital Region, and various office projects. In addition, the series on the Secure Commonwealth Panel represents an important function of the Office of Commonwealth Preparedness which operated under the chairmanship of the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. Significant series also relate to Constituent Correspondence & Correspondence. These series are invaluable in showing the concerns and interests of citizens, government officials, and other individuals regarding security, terrorism, and various other subjects.
Series I: Appointment Calendars, 2002-2006. The Appointment Calendars series is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order. This series consists of appointment calendars belonging to John H. Hager, and later George W. Foresman, Assistants to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. The calendars detail meetings and itinerary for conferences, symposiums, receptions, and various appointments. The calendars include names of contacts, phone numbers, memos, electronic mail, directions, correspondence, and agendas.
Series II: Cabinet Meeting Files, 2001-2005. The Cabinet Meeting Files series is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order. This series contains agendas, inaugural celebration information, budget outlook, memos, talking points, proposals, notes, correspondence, and reports. The correspondence included in this series originates from John H. Hager, Governor's Assistant of Commonwealth Preparedness; Bill Leighty, Chief of Staff; and Regina J. Payne, Special Assistant/Administrator to the Governor's Assistant of Commonwealth Preparedness, and is addressed to the cabinet secretaries. In addition, this series contains a transition team brief with press release, list of transition committee members, transition structure, contact information, and committee member resumes. Lastly, there is a governor-elect brief with agenda, briefing on crisis management, a briefing on public safety response to terrorism, terrorist preparedness & policy issues, emergency/disaster responsibilities of the Governor of Virginia, and Virginia Emergency Services & Disaster Laws.
Series III: Constituent Correspondence, 2002-2005. The Constituent Correspondence series is housed in seven archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order. This series contains correspondence from various constituents to Governor Mark W. Warner, along with a copy of John H. Hager's, and later George W. Foresman's, letter in response, and a page from the people summary database which includes the name, address, and phone number of the correspondent. Each letter in this series contains a unique tracking number assigned by the Governor's Office Constituent Services. The correspondence in this series relates to terrorism, 9/11, memorials, security, conferences, products, publications, organizations, the War with Iraq & Afghanistan, funding, the U.S. Patriot Act, immigration, grants, the Chesapeake-Bridge Tunnel, military bases realignment & closure, FBI Joint Terrorism Task Forces (JTTFs), intelligence issues, the Naval Air Station Oceana, Fort Monroe, Hurricane Katrina, and others.
Noteworthy correspondents includes Tommy G. Thompson, Secretary of Health & Human Services; Raymond F. Dubois, Jr., Deputy Under Secretary of Defense; Donald Rumsfeld, Secretary of Defense; Paul Wolfowitz, Deputy Secretary of Defense; Michael W. Wynne, Under Secretary of Defense; Paul McHale, Assistant Secretary of Defense; and Tom Ridge & Michael Chertoff, Directors of Homeland Security. Tommy G. Thompson writes regarding bioterrorism (2004694 - 2002 March; 2013873 - 2002 April; & 2030518 - 2002 June). Raymond F. Dubois, Jr., encloses a copy of a letter from Secretary Donald Rumsfeld regarding the Department of Defense's Readiness & Range Preservation Initiative (RRPI) (2021226 - 2002 May). Paul Wolfowitz writes regarding the transfer of World War II chemical warfare agents (2071803 - 2003 Jan.). Michael W. Wynne writes regarding the Defense Base Closure & Realignment Committee (2463864 - 2005 June). Paul McHale transmits the recently signed Strategy for Homeland Defense and Civil Support (2481709 - 2005 Aug.). Tom Ridge writes regarding the commencement of the new Department of Homeland Security (2097847 - 2003 Feb.), the transfer of the Office of Domestic Preparedness (2117507 - 2003 March), the Emergency Preparedness & Response Directorate (EPR) & the Office of Community Oriented Policing Services (COPS) (2163592 - 2003 June), National Preparedness Month (2324908 - 2004 July & 2365495 - 2004 Sept.), Virginia Commonwealth University's Homeland Security & Emergency Planning Program (2371317 - 2004 Nov.), and the disabled community in homeland security (2396646 - 2005 Jan.). Lastly, Michael Chertoff writes regarding a review of the Department of Homeland Security (2488508 - 2005 Aug.), the National Incident Management System (NIMS) implementation requirements (2509012 - 2005 Oct.), and National Preparedness Month (2513347 - 2004 Oct.).
Series IV: Correspondence, 2001-2006. The Correspondence series is housed in seven archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order with recommendation letters to the rear of the series. This series includes correspondence to John H. Hager, and later George W. Foresman, Assistants to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. The correspondence is similar to the above series Constituent Correspondence, except the correspondence was mainly sent directly to the Office of Commonwealth Preparedness, rather than the governor. The correspondence includes copies of the response letters from John Hager and George Foresman. The correspondence in this series relates to job applications, the Secure Virginia Panel, the BRAC Commission, Afghanistan, funding, conferences, security issues, employment, Hurricanes Isabel & Katrina, grant programs, the U.S. Department of Homeland Security, immigration, intelligence, products, bioterrorism, task forces, workshops, the Oceana Air Base, and the National Capitol Region's (NCR) Homeland Security Strategic Plan. Early correspondence addressed to John Hager congratulate him on his appointment as Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness. Also included in this series are recommendation letters addressed to Hager regarding employment opportunities between 2002 and 2003. These letters include Hager's response and often include resumesand gubernatorial employment applications. The recommendations also include Hager's correspondence to service academies, college admissions, government positions, etc.
Series V: Homeland Security Threat Conditions, 2003. The Homeland Security Threat Conditions series is housed in one archival folder and is arranged in chronological order. This series includes press releases and electronic mail regarding changes in Virginia's terrorist threat conditions by Governor Mark R. Warner. Also included is a booklet on terrorist threat conditions by the Commonwealth of Virginia Homeland Security. The booklet provides a description of each threat level and the necessary precautions at each level.
Series VI: Secure Commonwealth Panel, 2001-2005. The Secure Commonwealth Panel series is housed in ten archival boxes and is arranged in two subseries. Subseries have been designated for Administrative Files and Meeting Files. This series documents the work of the Secure Virginia Panel, which later became the Secure Commonwealth Panel.
Subseries A: Administrative Files, 2001-2005. The Administrative Files subseries is housed in four archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order by subject. This subseries mainly consists of files related to the various sub panels within the Secure Commonwealth Panel including the following: Agribusiness Sub Panel, Citizen & Communities Sub Panel, First Responder Sub Panel, Government Operations & Funding Sub Panel, Health & Medical Sub Panel, Industry & Commerce Sub Panel, Technology Sub Panel, Transportation Sub Panel, and Utilities Sub Panel. These files include meeting minutes and supporting documentation such as correspondence, reports, etc. The subseries also contains several files related to the various task forces formed by the Secure Commonwealth Panel including the Funding Task Force, the Intelligence & Information Sharing Task Force, the Mass Fatalities Task Force, the Performance Measures Task Force, and the Public/Private Cooperation Task Force. Lastly, there are files devoted to the Commonwealth Preparedness Working Group which includes meeting agendas, reports, attendance sheets, memos, and correspondence.
Subseries B: Meeting Files, 2002-2005. The Meeting Files subseries is housed in seven archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order. This subseries documents the monthly meetings of the Secure Virginia Panel, and later Secure Commonwealth Panel, established by Governor Warner to improve the Commonwealth's emergency preparedness, response, and recovery. The files contain agendas, briefings, electronic mail, lists of panel members, comments, rsvp lists, press releases, memos, meeting audio tapes, PowerPoint presentations on compact disc, reports, minutes, visitor sign-in sheets, motions to open & close meetings, and reimbursement vouchers. The electronic mail in this subseries was sent by Regina Payne, Executive Assistant to the Governor's Office for Commonwealth Preparedness, regarding Secure Virginia Panel meeting arrangements.
Series VII: Supporting Documentation, 1999-2005. The Supporting Documentation series is housed in twenty-four archival boxes and is arranged in five subseries. Subseries have been designated for Alphabetical Files, Base Realignment & Closure (BRAC), Homeland Security Grant Information, National Capital Region (NCR), and Office Projects.
Subseries A: Alphabetical Files, 2001-2005. The Alphabetical Files subseries is housed in six archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order. This subseries contains correspondence, grant applications, decision briefs, reports, speeches, legislation, minutes, appointments, memos, testimony, photographs, and other sundry items. Notable subjects include bioterrorism grants, the U.S. Department of Homeland Security Technology & Evaluation Program, the Gilmore Commission, the Office of Domestic Preparedness's Evaluation & Exercise Program, the Real ID Task Force, and the Virginia Military Institute.
Subseries B: Base Realignment & Closures (BRAC), 2003-2005. The Base Realignment & Closures subseries is housed in five archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order. This subseries includes files related to the closings of Cecil Field and the Naval Air Station Oceana (NASO). Correspondence within this subseries originates from Governor Warner, George Foresman, Anthony J. Principi, Chairman of the BRAC Commission, and Senator John Warner. Also abundant are files related to the Virginia Commission on Military Bases. These files include budget information, meeting agendas, minutes, memos, and bill tracking. Lastly, there are files related to the minutes of the Virginia Military Advisory Council.
Subseries C: Homeland Security Grant Information, 2000-2005. The Homeland Security Grant Information subseries is housed in four archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order. This subseries contains grant proposals, correspondence, memos, grant award announcements, reports, grant applications, presentations, and worksheets. The Urban Areas Security Initiative (UASI) and Virginia Port Authority grant programs are the most plentiful files in this subseries.
Subseries D: National Capital Region (NCR), 2002-2005. The National Capital Region subseries is housed in five archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order. This subseries contains correspondence, reports, presentations, testimony, statements, resolutions, memos, agendas, meeting summaries, fact sheets, recommendations, and minutes. The Department of Homeland Security Office for National Capital Region was established by H.R. 5005 to oversee and coordinate Federal programs and relationships with state, local, & regional authorities in the National Capital Region.
Subseries E: Office Projects, 1999-2005. The Office Projects subseries is housed in four archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order. This subseries contains correspondence, grant information, certifications, plans, reports, action statements, meeting notes, and presentations. Noteworthy files include the Continuity of Operations Plan (COOP), the Driver Licensing & Identification Card Issuance Task Force, and the Virginia Preparedness & Security Panel. The COOP files mostly include certifications of compliance from the various directors of state agencies, colleges, etc. The Driver Licensing & Identification Card Issuance Task Force files include action statements, background, meeting notes, minutes, attendance lists, agendas, and summary notes. The background files include information on legislation such as HB1954 & S1058 which require the Department of Motor Vehicles to verify the citizenship or legal status of every applicant for either an identification card or an original driver's license. Also included as the implementation of legislation, press releases, lists of acceptable documents as proof of legal presence, and reports. The action/issue statements provide a short description of the action or issue regarding driver licensing & identification card issuance, the decision issue, impacts & challenges, and the DMV recommended decision. Lastly, the Virginia Preparedness & Security Panel includes reports and background information of the panel established by Governor James Gilmore in 1999 by section 44-146.17 of the Code of Virginia to assess & make suggestions regarding the level of preparedness & security necessary to protect the citizens, property, assets, & resources of the Commonwealth from the effects or consequences of an actual terrorist act or the threat of terrorism.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Appointment Calendars, Cabinet Meeting Files, Constituent Correspondence, Correspondence, Homeland Security Threat Conditions, Secure Commonwealth Panel, and Supporting Documentation.
Contents List
- Series I: Appointment Calendars, 2002-2006
  - 2002
    - January-June (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - July-December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2003
    - January-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - July-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2004
    - January-June (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - July-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2005
    - January-March (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - April-August (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - September-December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II: Cabinet Meeting Files, 2001-2005
  - 2001 - Transition Team Brief (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 2002
    - Governor-Elect Brief (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - January (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - February (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - March (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - April (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - May (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - June (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - July (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - August (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - September (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - October (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - November (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - December (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 2003
    - Cabinet Input Matrix (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - January (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - February (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - March (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - April (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - May (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - June (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - July (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - August (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - September (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - October (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - November (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - December (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 2004
    - January (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - March (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - April (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - October (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - November (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 2005
    - March (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - May (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - August (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - December (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Series III: Constituent Correspondence, 2002-2005
  - 2002
    - February (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - March (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - April (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - May (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - June (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - July (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - August (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - September (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - October (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - November (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - December (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 2003
    - January (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - February (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - March
      - 2101273-2118141 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 2118159-21122867 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - April (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - May (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - June (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - July (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - August (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - September (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - October (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - November (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - December (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 2004
    - January (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - February (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - March (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - April (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - May (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - June (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - July (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - August (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - September (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - October (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - November (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - December (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 2005
    - January (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - February (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - March (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - April (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - May (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - June
      - 2451612-2455656 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - 2451612-2455656 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 2455840-2455864 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - 2455866-2455906 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 2455908-2456400 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - 2456410-2458682 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - 2451612-2455656 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - 2464126-2470405 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - July
      - 2474210-2474936 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - 2474941-2481750 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - August
      - 2473374-2481715 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 2481801-2484698 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - 2485178-2492130 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - September
      - 2488095-2482817 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - 2492825-2494181 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - 2494372-2501465 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - October
      - 2494315-2501450 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - 2501730-2513347 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - November (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - December (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Correspondence, 2001-2006
  - 2001 December (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 2002
    - January (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - February
      - 1-8 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - 11-21 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - 22-28 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - March
      - 1-11 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - 15-29 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - April (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - May
      - 1-16 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - 17-31 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - June (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - July (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - August (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - September (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - October
      - 1-24 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - 25-31 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - November (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - December (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 2003
    - January (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - February (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - March (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - April (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - May (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - June (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - July (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - August (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - September (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - October (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - November (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - December (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 2004
    - January (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - February (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - March (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - April (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - May (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - June (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - July (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - August (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - September (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - October (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - November (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - December (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - 2005
    - January (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - February (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - March (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - April (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - May (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - June (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - July (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - August (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - September (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - October (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - December (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 2006
    - January (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Recommendation Letters
    - 2002
      - Feb. 6-March 22 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - March 28-Oct. 28 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - 2003 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Seires V: Homeland Security Threat Conditions, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Secure Commonwealth Panel Files, 2001-2005
  - Subseries A: Administrative Files, 2001-2005
    - Agribusiness Sub Panel
      - Meeting Minutes, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Supporting Documentation, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 3)